<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3633 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4580 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4580.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4649 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4649.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4704 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4704.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4776 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4776.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4941 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6355 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6355.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6939 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6939.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6973 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.krishnan-dhc-dhcpv6-privacy SYSTEM
"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.krishnan-dhc-dhcpv6-privacy.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mrugalski-dhc-dhcpv6-privacy-mitigation-00"
     updates="3315" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DHCPv6 Privacy Concerns Mitigation">Mitigation of Privacy
    Concerns in DHCPv6</title>

    <author fullname="Tomek Mrugalski" initials="T." surname="Mrugalski">
      <organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium,
      Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94063</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tomasz.mrugalski@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!--
    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 Decarie Blvd.</street>
          <city>Town of Mount Royal</city>
          <region>QC</region>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 514 345 7900 x42871</phone>
        <email>suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> -->

    <!--
    <author fullname="Sheng Jiang" initials="S." surname="Jiang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus, No.156 BeiQing Road</street>
          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jiangsheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> -->

    <!--
    <author fullname="Bernie Volz" initials="B" surname="Volz">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave</street>
          <city>Boxborough, MA  01719</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>volz@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> -->

    <!--
    <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C" surname="Huitema">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>huitema@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> -->


    <date year="2014" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>dhc</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t><xref target="I-D.krishnan-dhc-dhcpv6-privacy" /> discusses
      various privacy considerations in DHCPv6. This draft explores
      several migitation techniques. This draft is expected to evolve
      significantly over time, but the ultimate goal is to standardize
      mitigation techniques the DHC working group considers useful.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> is a protocol that is used to
      provide addressing and configuration information to IPv6 hosts. The
      DHCPv6 protocol uses several identifiers that could become a source for
      gleaning additional information about the IPv6 host. This information
      may include device type, operating system information, location(s) that
      the device may have previously visited, etc. This document discusses the
      various identifiers used by DHCPv6 and the potential privacy issues
      <xref target="RFC6973"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Future works may propose protocol changes to fix the privacy issues
      that have been analyzed in this document. It is out of scope for this
      document.</t>

      <t>Editor notes: for now, the document is mainly considering the privacy
      of DHCPv6 client. The privacy of DHCPv6 server and relay agent are
      considered less important because they are open for public services.
      However, this may be a subject to change if further study shows opposite
      result.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This section clarifies the terminology used throughout this
      document.</t>

      <t>Stable identifier - any property disclosed by a DHCPv6 client that
      does not change over time or changes very infrequently and is unique for
      said client in a given context. Examples include MAC address, client-id
      that does not change or a hostname. Stable identifier may or may not be
      globally unique.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>. When these words are not in ALL CAPS (such as
      "should" or "Should"), they have their usual English meanings, and are
      not to be interpreted as <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> key words.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Client Mitigation Techniques">

      <section anchor="desire" title="Not disclose the desire for privacy">
	<t>Naive approach to privacy would be to disclose the desire
	to protect one's privacy, for example by sending requests for
	temporary addresses or defining a new type of temporary DUID
	that would be changing over time. This leads to a logical
	fallacy. It has to be assumed that the network operator (or
	other entities that have access to the operator's network) is
	actively participating in surveillance and anti-privacy,
	willingly or not. By simply relealing the desire for privacy,
	an operator could counter-react by triggering additional
	surveillance or monitoring mechanisms. Therefore is more
	preferable to not disclose one's preference for privacy.</t>

	<t>This fact has important implications. In particular, all
	mitigation techniques should be indistinguishable from
	regular client behaviors, if possible.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="random-duid" title="Randomized DUID">
	<t>One of the primary privacy concerns is that a client is
	disclosing a stable itentifier that can be use for tracking
	and behavior profiling. The most obvious way of disclosing
	client's MAC/hardware address in DHCPv6 is to use DUID type
	LLT (link-layer with time) or LL (link-layer). Another DUID
	type - UUID - is also bad in this regards, as its the UUID
	may contain additional information about the device it is
	tied to.</t>
	<t>Discussion: As stated in <xref target="desire"/>, the
	desire for privacy should not be explicitly
	advertised. Therefore a new DUID type is not recommended
	here.</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: The clients willing to protect its privacy SHOULD
	generate a new randomized DUID-LLT every time they attach to a
	new link or detect a possible link change event. Details are
	left up to implementors, but several factors should be taken
	into consideration. Duid type SHOULD be set to 1
	(DUID-LLT). Hardware type SHOULD be set appropriately to the
	hardware type.  Time MAY be set to current time, but this will
	reveal the fact that the DUID is new. Implementors interested
	in hiding that fact MAY use past time stamp. For example a
	random timestamp in the last year seems like a good value. In
	the most common cases the link-layer address is based on
	MAC. The first three bytes are OUI (Organizationally Unique
	Identifier) that is expected to have a value assigned to a
	real organization. See <xref target="IEEE-OUI" /> for currently
	assigned values. Using a value that is unassinged may disclose
	the fact that a DUID is randomized. Using a value that belongs
	to a third party may have legal implications.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Do not send Confirm">
	<t>The <xref target="RFC3315" /> states that a client must
	send Confirm message when link attachement may have
	changed. While moving to a different location, legacy clients
	send Confirm message with its old address, thus revealing
	previous location.</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: Clients interested in protecting their privacy
	SHOULD NOT send Confirm.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Obtaining temporary addresses">
	<t><xref target="RFC3315" /> defines special container (IA_TA)
	for requesting temporary addresses. This is a good mechanism
	in principle, but there are a number of issues associated with
	it. First, this is not widely used feature, so clients
	depending solely on temporary addresses may lock themselves
	out of service. Second, the <xref target="RFC3315" /> does not
	specify renewal mechanisms for temporary addresses. Therefore
	support for renewing temporary addresses may vary between
	server implementations, including not being supported at
	all. Finally, by using temporary addresses, a client reveals
	its desire to be anonymous or at least being privacy
	conscious. If network operator participates in counter-privacy
	operation, he may conduct actions to defeat the purpose of
	using temporary addresses.</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: Clients interested in increasing their privacy
	SHOULD not use IA_TA. They should send IA_NA with a randomized
	IAID. This, along with the mitigation technique discussed in
	<xref target="random-duid"/>, will ensure that a client will
	get a new address that can be renewed, so can be used as long
	as needed. To get a new address, it can send Request message
	with a new randomized IAID before releasing the other
	one. This will cause the server to assign a new address, as it
	still has a valid lease for the old IAID value. Once a new
	address is assigned, the one using old IAID value can be
	released safely, using Release message.</t>
	<t>This proposal may not work if the server enforces specific
	policies, e.g. only one address per client. If client does not
	succeed in receiving a second address using a new IAID, it may
	release the first one (using an old IAID) and then retry
	asking for a new address.</t>

	<t>From the Operating System perspective, addresses obtained
	using this technique SHOULD be treated as temporary as
	specified in <xref target="RFC4941" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Do not request FQDN">
	<t>A typical client uses FQDN option, defined in <xref
	target="RFC4704" /> to negotiate with a server the DNS entries
	that should be updated. In the process, the client typically
	reveals its hostname and possibly its home domain. Server,
	depending on configured policies, may accept or override the
	name with network specific information.</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: Client SHOULD avoid disclosing its hostname as
	it may contain personally identifiers (e.g. "Tomek's laptop")
	and even it doesn't, it may still be used for
	tracking. Therefore a client SHOULD not send FQDN option at
	all. This eliminate that velue of information leakage, but has
	a disavantage of not having a resolvable DNS name. Should DNS
	name be useful, a client SHOULD send a randomly generated
	hostname, consisting of a single label. The server is expected
	to append domain name and return FQDN to the client. Client
	can then use that value as its temporary hostname that will
	be discarded once its location changes or the client choses to
	assume a new identity.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Options order matters">
	<t>A DHCPv6 client may reveal other types of information,
	besides unique identifiers. There are many ways a DHCPv6
	client can conduct certain actions. The specifics can be used
	to fingerprint the client. This will not reveal the identity
	of a client, but may give additional information, e.g. device
	type, vendor type or OS type and in some cases specific
	version.</t>

	<t>One specific method used for fingerprinting is the order in
	which options are included in the message. Another related is
	the order of option codes included in ORO (Option Request
	Option).</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: The client willing to protect its privacy SHOULD
	randomize options order before sending any DHCPv6
	message. Such a client SHOULD also randomly shuffle the
	option codes order in ORO.</t>

	<!-- tomek: I also briefly thought about paranoid type of
	a client that could ask in ORO for other random options.
	That would be sort of fun, but may have adverse effects in the
	long term. There may be options defined in the future that
	could affect how DHCPv6 operates (e.g. client supporting
	feature X should request option Y.). So this has a potential
	for too much (random) breakage in the future. -->
      </section>

      <section title="Anonymous Information-Request">
	<t>According to <xref target="RFC3315" />, a DHCPv6 client
	typically includes its client identifier in most of the
	messages it sends. There is one exception, however. Client is
	allowed to omit its client identifier when sending
	Information-Request.</t>

	<t>PROPOSAL: When using stateless DHCPv6, clients willing to
	protect their privacy SHOULD not include client identifiers in
	their Information-Request messages. This will prevent the
	server from specifying client-specific options if it is
	configured to do so, but that's the point of protecting one's
	privacy.</t>
      </section>

    </section>


    <section title="Server Mitigation Techniques">
      <t>TODO:
      - don't send GEOLOCATION options to anyone who asks (preferably
        don't sent that option at all);
      - if running on mobile device, possibly change its server-id
        when its link flips;
      - don't send FQDN options if you don't intend to do actual
        DNS Updates;
      - </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy-consider" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This document at its entirety discusses privacy considerations in
      DHCPv6. As such, no separate section about this is needed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This draft does not request any IANA action.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thanks the valuable comments made by
      Stephen Farrell, Ted Lemon, Ines Robles, Russ White, Christian Schaefer
      and other members of DHC WG.</t>

      <t>This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool <xref
      target="RFC2629"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc3315;

      &I-D.krishnan-dhc-dhcpv6-privacy;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3633;

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2629'?>

      &rfc4580;

      &rfc4649;

      &rfc4704;

      &rfc4776;

      &rfc4941;

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5007'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5460'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5970'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6225'?>

      &rfc6355;

      &rfc6939;

      &rfc6973;

      &I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy;

      <reference anchor="IEEE-OUI">
        <front>
          <title>Organizationally Unique Identifiers
          http://www.ieee.org/netstorage/standards/oui.txt</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IEEE</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
